hey guys welcome to concept and coding
and this is Shan and today we are going
to do the second topic of a spring boot
setting up our project and I will also
tell you about the layered architecture
which spring boot generally we follow
okay so let's start without wasting any
time setting up the spring boot project
is very very easy that that's my
experience right after this session when
you try to set up let me know your
experience also like do you find it easy
or hard right so how you can set up is
first you can directly go to Spring
initializer URL so this is the URL
start.
spring.io so this type of page will get
open okay so what you have to do is you
have to select the language so I'm
comfortable with Java so I'm using Java
and the dependency like so Mayan I
generally Ed as a dependency all the
management and all so you can choose
either gradel and MAV whichever you like
right so I generally uh follow Mayan
okay so if you don't know Mayan don't
worry if you uh know from our playlist
or like we will discuss about the Mayan
in depth uh at least how our uh Mayan
architecture or pal. XML looks like okay
so I have choosen Mayan for that one
project choose the version of a spring
boot so let's pick the latest one
3.2.3 okay so fill up these details your
project metadata so these uh group and
artifact is something which uniquely
identifies your project okay so
generally group is something your com
company name and anything so I just use
com. concept and coding artifact is
generally uh the project name right so I
have just given the name as a learning
spring board you can give anything right
the group but combining group and
artifact
individually identifies a particular
project okay this name and description
we can give accordingly what project we
are building okay so ultimately this is
how our package name going to look
like okay so after this one you have to
decide the packaging jar or VAR if
anybody who don't know what's the
difference between jar and V and when to
use so just one minute so that I will
explain this one it will get clarifies
to you so jar means Java
archive VAR means a web archive so in
the world of
microservices and stand wherever you
need stand alone Java
application you have to use only jar
right
when I say that what do this mean by
Standalone Java application let's say
that we are writing one application Java
application and we just started it
server that's all so this is a stand
alone application it doesn't need
anything else you send it the request it
will give you the response but in case
of V you need let's say the complete web
archive like
HTML
CSS
JavaScript some JSP pages right if you
need a complete bundle complete package
for the web application then it is then
go for war right we used to use it way
back long but nowadays in the world of
microservices each micro each component
each microservice is an individual
Standalone
application okay so in today's world
mostly you will find we are using jar
only Java archive which are Java stand
alone application you don't need HTML
CSS JavaScript everything to be buden
together no alone Java Java classes its
libraries all its resources that's
all pick the Java version which you are
comfortable with it so uh giving two
options 17 21 I picked 17 okay and then
there comes the dependencies so for now
I have chosen one dependency spring WB
so spring WB says that uh help in
building the web restful apis right uh
we will get the embedded uh server uh
subet container Tomcat right so we are
getting all these things so this is
basic sufficient to create a web
application microser we can create a
server with with this spring web okay
let's say that we want to connect with
DB and all there would be more like a
spring
jpa is so so we can add more
dependencies directly in the May one if
required so just for the starting
setting of the project we can start with
one so in our Mayan pom.xml
only initial dependency will get added
for this one and as soon as we progress
we required more dependency we will add
in our mavan pom.xml file okay and after
that you will there will be one generate
option you can generate it and the
project will get downloaded to your
system now you can open your favorite ID
my favorite ID is
intellig and you know that those who are
using intellig there is another way of
setting up the spring boot project is uh
you can click on the file in the new you
will see project and when you click on
the project there is something called
Spring right so it is not available in
the community version it is available in
the ultimate version I think it required
uh some payment but uh for Community
version this is logged okay so those who
have ultimate version they can even
create a spring boot directly from their
system uh from their ID itself or
otherwise you can just simply uh do open
you can just uh open the project right
which you which is
downloaded so the downloaded would
contain so these all things which I have
written this will not be there so it
would be this would be ultimately get
downloaded when you open the project
which is downloaded in the ID so these
two things you will get a pal and you
will get a spring boot
application class that's all and this is
the package which we have defined there
right so this simple very basic things
now comes into this if if you uh run it
your if you run this Tomcat started okay
server is getting started right but
since we haven't return any control or
anything nothing would uh you can't hit
any API but project setup that
easily okay all you see that all the
dependencies whichever we have set it's
available here only two dependencies
comes with the
web uh this one and the test two writing
the uh unit test cases if we requireed
more in future we can add more
here
okay so setting up the project is that
easy in a
springboard and one thing also today I
will uh wanted to explain you is what is
layered architecture in a springboard
okay so in a spring boot generally this
layered architecture is something which
is uh mostly used used right and in many
mnc's big mnc's you will find this
layered architecture only so what is
this layer architecture so let's say
these are the clients they are hitting
any
API okay so this is the first layer
which is controller layer so this
controller layer has all the classes
which has annotation like at the rate
controller at the rate rest controller
like this so these are the uh classes
which host your end points right like
like we have seen previously like like
slash payment slash payment SL Su endo1
like these all classes only host that
API and client hit that API right they
will interact your component with the
these apis itself and controller layer
is the first starting point uh which
host those
apis second layer is your service layer
so these classes generally has at theate
service
annotation and this is where we put our
business
logic so all your business logic
whatever patterns whatever the business
specific
logic anywhere anything which you have
to put you have to put inside the
service layer right not in controller
not in repository service
layer this is the third layer which is
called repository layer so there
generally you will find classes which is
annotated with like atate repository
annotations and its work is to connect
with the
DB right so maybe my SQL maybe no SQL
whatever so this layer actually interact
with the DB F the data and return to the
service layer or if it has to insert
repository layer takes the
responsibility to insert the data also
so so repository layer generally and
should be interacted with DB so many
times people what uh we do is we from
service layer also we sometimes start
doing get calls and insert calls into
the DB see nobody is stopping it right
we can do whatever we want
but it's un not you can say that the
correct way of doing it as for the layer
architecture repository layer should be
the one which should touch
TV okay so apart from this three layers
there are certain uh other you can say
that packages which we create as a
spring so one very important is this
dto this is not a layer this is you can
say that the additional packages we
create okay so one is dto what is
dto let me explain
you okay okay so see dto is generally
you can say the data transfer object
okay so now let's say that client is
hitting certain post
API and they are uh sending certain body
the data in the body let's say certain
ID 1 2 3 uh certain number uh number
card uh card number let's say certain my
card number 5 4 3 2 1 so certain
information coming it from the post API
the client which is sending so in the
dto data transfer object so generally
there are two type we can create one is
request
dto one is
response dto so in the request dto what
we do is we map the data which is coming
from the client or outside of our
component to this dto request dto so
that our business layer
repository whatever going to work with
going to work with the request GTO not
with the fields which are coming from
the external API like the clients which
you are initiating why because let's say
that in future the schema got changed
and let's say it's ID name got changed
to certain uh certain this thing like
identif ification from ID name change to
identification or let's say sequence
number okay so we have to change it all
the places where this uh ID is used so
it has to be changed to sequence number
but if you're are using request dto then
at the controller layer itself so
controller layer takes the
responsibility of doing the
mapping
from uh the
parameters from API parameter
to request dto and now everywhere
everyone works on the request dto so
only this controller class will get
impacted if any of the schema got
changed because this is the place where
we are doing the
mapping okay similarly the response dto
so now let's say that service layer
calls the resp uh repository layer hey
fetch me the data repository layer get
the data and return it is it a good way
that in the DB let's say if we have a
column name as uh card certain card ID
let's say I'm just taking that say it's
card ID so is it a good way that we
return the card ID in the response
itself our DB column name no so what we
do is the service layer do the mapping
whatever the values which are coming
from repository of DB map it to the
response dto what ultimately goes out of
your system right and we will map it and
return it in the response dto okay so
you got like what DTS is data data
transfer
object then utility utility is like in
the utility as the name says that put
anything which is common across service
layer or repository in service layer you
might be creating multiple classes class
one class 2 class CL three class 4 and
they might be have they might want to
use certain common
method right so that common method we
can put into utility generally helper
methods so they can call that utility
methods so generally utility method you
can say that helper methods which is
generally common among more than one
classes okay then you have entity so in
the entity it's uh so classes generally
annotated with like this annotation
entity and these are the pojos and let's
say for example class
employee so now let's say it has
uh
ID string employee name and the Getters
and Setters so just a pojo certain
Fields ID name and it's get get method
and set method and we have annotated
with at theate entity so this is a
direct representation of our
table which table employee
table employee table would have two
column one would be ID another would be
name right so this entity whatever the
classes we put into the entity packages
they are the direct representation of
our table and what generally happen is
let's say you want want to insert the
data service layer want to insert the
data so what they do is they will create
an object of entity they put the values
here and then call repository they said
insert this object like so now
internally whether jdbc jpa which you
are using they will ultimately map to
the corresponding columns and the table
they will update it similarly when you
are fetching the data from the
repository so it has to Let's uh you are
fetching uh
select estess from employee something
now it will return certain
rows let's say list of what list of what
it will return some rows right list of
what list of this employee
entity list of employee entity this
query will ultimately return so our
spring jpa jdbc internally do this
mapping so we will come to that point
how they do it but understand that What
entity is entity is just classes which
are direct representation of our tables
so they have the same field name is
exactly the same what we have in the
column of that particular table so they
are just normal simple pojo classes
fields and they're getter and
Setter right so generally entities are
used by repositories mostly
and then we have configuration so there
is something called
application dotproperty files we will
see that so there we can put
configuration
so like certain you want to increase uh
certain timeout value uh or you want so
there are lot of configurations comes in
right so in our code let's say uh you
want to put certain value let's say int
Val equals to 10 this hardcoded
generally is avoided in your code base
there should not be any hardcoded value
it should be driven through
configuration so that in future it can
be changed without doing code
changes okay so that's where we can put
a configuration in application do
properties we can put that okay let's
say that value equals to 10 today okay
and in here we can use instead of 10
certain like config do value I'm just
taking so that it will read from config
it will read that value in future you
need to change from 10 to uh let's say
20 you don't need code changes you don't
need code changes simply config do value
right in the config you can change it no
code changes required we can directly
push the
configuration okay so this is the
generally the layered
architecture okay so I've created
controller so created a controller so
this controller package has the class
which has at theate rest
controller okay so it has one get
mapping ID so now what it will do first
so this ID right so what first it is
doing
is using the
dto right so what I am doing is so here
payment request is a dto this is a
request dto because I am not forwarding
this ID into my service layer because if
in future this ID value get changed I
don't want my service layer to get
change also so in the dto first I set
this so in I'm setting this value into
here in my internal
dto okay so first mapping is done then
what controller do does is it passes to
the service layer that hey F get the
payment details by ID then this is my
internal dto go ahead now the request
goes
to your service this is the service
payment service so what payment service
do is payment service interact with the
repository so there it has dependency on
repository so it tells repository that
hey get the payment by this ID and this
is the
dto right and uh
it goes to the repository so this is the
repository as payment repository so here
if you see at theate repository and on
the service atate service was
there so now what repository will do
repository has to connect with the DB
and fetch the details so for example
execute query I have just return that it
will connect with DB and F the data we
will see how it will connect maybe in
the later classes uh but uh in the this
session we will see that okay assume
that it connected to the DB and FDA data
so ultimately the data comes into the
hit the query and we get into the entity
because in Java everything is object
right whatever the data you get from DB
you will get into some object so that's
where I created entity payment entity so
let's say that I have a table which has
this
four 1 2 3 4 uh details so it will
return me certain entity okay and
ultimately what it will do is it will
return this entity back to the
service now what service will do Serv
service will do a
mapping mapping
from our entity which correspond to our
DB table to the response dto so here
payment response so this is our dto and
but the response resp okay so the in
this Fields I will send back to the
client so this Fields name would be
different than what my DB tables names
are uh DB table column names are so but
I do just a mapping so okay and after
doing the mapping the uh
service returns to
the your controller ultimately it goes
to the controller and what controller
will do it will send the response back
okay to the client and send the
response a spring boot application now
let's started so started now let's hit
this API so my Tom cut started on 8080
now let's see hit it so see we got the
response payment
ID amount currency and all so this might
be details get from DB and we return in
the response so in the payment
repository we have set this values right
so we assume that we get this data from
DB in the entity and then we return
back right and here if you see that I am
setting here set payment amount payment
amount but the what field I'm getting
amount why because I have done a mapping
in the service uh service layer right so
I have done a mapping this
amount currency so these fields are
different than one my DB DB uh table
column
say okay so if you have any issue with
setting up this project uh let's discuss
in the comment section man okay thank
you
bye